Finding Aid of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration Records LSC.1041
UCLA Library Special Collections
United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration records
1945-1948
UCLA Library Special Collections
United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration
LSC.1041
8.5 Linear Feet (17 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942339033606533
Scope and Content
Collection consists of research materials, pamphlets, newspapers, press releases, books, news bulletins, art prints, and ephemera distributed by the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency (UNRRA) and collected by David N. Leff while on assignment with the UNRRA Mission in Yugoslavia. Many of the pamphlets and periodicals are in Russian, Serbo-Croation, French, and other languages.
Expanded Scope and Content Note
This collection consists largely of research materials collected by David Leff while on assignment with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency (UNRRA) in Yugoslavia. The bulk of the collection is composed of pamphlets, newspapers, press releases, and news bulletins distributed by UNRRA, covering the years 1945-1948. Though much of the material is in English, many of the pamphlets and periodicals are in Russian, Serbo-Croatian, and various other languages.
Items Removed from Collection
London, Jack. Iron heel (Penguin, paperback copy).
The Communist: Organ of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (1 copy of each issue in collection). Placed in the Extremist Collection (Collection 50). Available in Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Fast, Howard. The Incredible Tito (1 copy).
Borba. Organ Komunisticke Partije Jugoslavije (incomplete). Belgrade, May 1, 1947-February 2, 1948 (A complete bound copy of Borba, 1945-1962, is available in the Young Research Library, newspaper stacks).
Yugoslavia -- History, 1945-1980 -- Archives.; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration -- Archives
- Book Materials
  - Research materials for a book, arranged in folders by planned chapter. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Materials include newspapers, excerpts from the Jugoslavia Basic Handbook, photographs, pamphlets, bulletins, some manuscript material, letters, periodicals, clippings, excerpts from articles and reports, and news bulletins.
    Chapter headings are:
    1) "Old Jugoslavia"
    2) "Axis Onslaught"
    3) "Occupation"
    4) "Partisan Resistance"
    5) "Mihailovic -- Hoax or Hero?"
    6) "Chronicle of War"
    7) "People's Authority"
    8) "Old Order Changeth"
    9) "Federated People's Republic"
    10) "Gentle Revolution"
    11) "New Democracy"
    12) "Lifeboat of State"
    13) "UNRRA"
    14) "New Deal, South Slav Style"
    15) "Plan and People"
    16) "Russian Question"
    17) "Neighbors"
    18) "Clouds in the West"
  - Notes on index cards -- probably arranged for the book., (3 bundles) (Box 2)
  - Notebook, March 10-23, 1945. (Box 2)
  - Bibliography of The Gentle Revolution, by David N. Leff. n.p., n.d.; (Typescript, 13 leaves) (Box 2)
    Also a carbon copy.
  - Key to bibliography, n.p., n.d.; (Typescript, 1 leaf) (Box 2)
    Also 3 carbon copies.
  - Letter from Thomas A. Bailey to David N. Leff. Stanford, January 3, 1941.; (Holograph, 1 leaf) (Box 2)
    Including enclosure.
  - Orders and passes, 1944-1945.; (8 items) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera., (8 items) (Box 2)
  - Metal signs, saying "Dangerous to lean out" in various languages., (5 items) (Box 2)
- Documents and Reports
  - The Progress of Reconstruction in Jugoslavia. UNRRA Jugoslav Mission, Economic Reporting Division, January-June 1946. (Box 2)
    Press releases on Economic Subjects issued by the Ministry of Information, F.P.R. of Jugoslavia:
    Report no.1, January 1946.
    Report no.2, February 1946.
    Report no.3, March/April 1946.
    Report no.4, May/June 1946.
  - Monthly Mission Report. UNRRA Jugoslav Mission, Belgrade. Office of Public Information, May 1945-June 1946; August-November 1946.; (18 items) (Box 3)
  - Monthly Mission Report. UNRRA Jugoslav Mission, Belgrade. Office of Public Information, December 1946-March 1947.; (4 items) (Box 4)
  - "Survey of Distribution of UNRRA supplies, " UNRRA Jugoslav Mission: Division of field operations and distribution., January-May 1946. (Box 4)
  - "Distribution and rationing of supplies in Jugoslavia: Report of the distribution control unit" (n.d., postdates )., December 26, 1946 (Box 4)
  - "UNRRA Jugoslav Mission: Historical monograph on UNRRA regional office for Bosnia and Hercegovina at Sarajevo." By Barratt-Brown, Michael. Belgrade, April 1947.; (132 leaves) (Box 4)
  - "60,000 Young Jugoslavs build a railway line." By Leff, David N. UNRRA Jugoslav Mission: Office of Public Information, Belgrade, September 1946. (Box 4)
- Confidential Material (English)
  - The Cetniks, a survey of cetnik activity in Yugoslavia, April 1941-June 1944. G-2 (Pb), A.F.H.Q., September 1944.; (2 vol.) (Box 4)
  - The National Liberation Movement of Yugoslavia: a survey of the Partisan movement, April 1941-March 1944. P.I.C.M.E., June 1944.; (2 copies) (Box 4)
- Secret Material - Jugoslavia Basic Handbook
  - Supplement..., January 1944. (Box 4)
  - Population of Jugoslavia, (based on data available, June 1946. (Box 4)
  - Part 1 - Pre-Invasion, August 1943. (Box 4)
  - Part 2 - Post-Invasion, August 1943. (Box 4)
  - Map section, August 1943. (Box 4)
- Division of Operational Analysis, UNRRA European Regional Office
  - Transport rehabilitation in Jugoslavia (Operational Analysis papers, no.27), February 1947. (Box 4)
  - Distribution of UNRRA supplies in Jugoslavia (Operational Analysis papers, no.29), March 1947. (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Documents (Dittoed)
  - II. Food, n.d; (13 leaves) (Box 4)
  - The problem of nationalities in Yugoslavia in the light of the national Liberation struggle, December 1942.; (7 leaves) (Box 4)
  - Yugoslavia from Versailles to Paris. By Vladimir Dedijer, n.d.; (5 leaves) (Box 4)
  - An interview with General McLean. Translated from "Nova Jugoslavia" (p.13), n.f., (7 leaves) (Box 4)
  - Declaration of Dr. Subasic's Government (p.98), August 7, 1944.; (6 leaves) (Box 4)
  - Jugoslav commercial agreements with other countries. UNRRA-Jugoslav Mission: Statistics branch., July 8, 1946.; (1 leaf, carbon copy) (Box 4)
  - Jugoslav War Crimes Commission. Report to the International Tribunal, Nuernberg., (87 leaves) (Box 5)
  - Jugoslav War Crimes Commission. Report to the International Tribunal, Nuernberg., ([33] leaves) (Box 5)
  - Jugoslav Document Book (miscellaneous documents - translated into English). (Box 5)
  - Explanatory Notes on Jugoslav Documents., ([6] leaves) (Box 5)
  - "Report on Italian crimes against Yugoslavia and its Peoples." State Commission for the investigation of war crimes. Belgrade, 1946.; (199pp.) (Box 5)
  - "Les sacrifices de la Yougoslavie en vies humaines et en beins dans l' effort de guerre de " Commission des Réparations de la République Fédérative Populaire de Yougoslavie., 1941-1945.; (57pp.) (Box 5)
  - "The debate on the budget for 1946." Speeches made by the ministers of the government of the F.P.R.J. Ministry of Information. Belgrade, April 1946.; (92pp.) (Box 5)
  - "The war effort of Yugoslavia, " The Military-Historical Institute of the Federated People's Republic of Yugoslavia., 1941-1945.; (41pp. and 5 fold-out maps) (Box 5)
  - "People's youth of Yugoslavia" (in 3 languages). (Box 5)
  - Yugoslavia (vol.1, no.1). Belgrade, October 1947. (Box 5)
  - Memorandum of the regional national liberation committee for the Slovene littoral and Trieste., (23 leaves) (Box 5)
  - Memorandum of the government of the Federative People's Republic of Yugoslavia on the economic problem of Trieste., (16 leaves) (Box 5)
  - Annex to the memorandum of the government of the Federative People's Republic of Yugoslavia on the economic problem of Trieste. (Box 5)
- Daily News Bulletins, (Carbon copies)
  - June-December 1945., (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - January-June 1946. (Box 7)
  - July-November 1946., (Ditto copies) (Box 8)
  - December 1946-January 1947. (Box 9)
  - January-February 1947. (Box 10)
  - February-April 1947. (Box 11)
  - April-May 1497. (Box 12)
  - News bulletins (no.7-9), Published by TANJUG (Telegraphic Agency New Yugoslavia)., April 26, 28, & May 1, 1949.; (3 items) (Box 12)
  - News clippings (Various papers and periodicals), v.d.; (11 folders) (Box 12)
    re Communism, Eastern Europe, Yugoslavia, and related subjects.
  - "Budget speeches,", 1947. (Box 12)
    Also 5-year plan. Included are Jugoslav newspapers, (scattered issues), and dittoed material.
- United Nations Materials
  - Charter of the United Nations, together with the Statute of the International Court of Justice. San Francisco, 1945. (Box 12)
  - Tomasevich, Jozo. "Postwar Economic Relations." In Yugoslavia: Foreign Economic Relations, 1918-1941. University of California Press, 1949. (Box 12)
    General note
    (Reprint from United Nations Series)
- UNRRA Materials
  - First session of the Council of the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration. Selected documents: Atlantic City, New Jersey, November 10-December 1, 1943. (Box 12)
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration: Resolutions adopted by the Council at its second session, held at Montreal, September 16-26, 1944. London (Box 12)
  - UNRRA at work (no.1-6). London, June 1946. (Box 12)
    "UNRRA: Structure and operations"
    "UNRRA in Greece"
    "UNRRA in Jugoslavia"
    "UNRRA in Albania"
    "UNRRA in Poland"
    "UNRRA in Czechoslovakia"
  - A compilation of the resolutions on policy: Fifth session of the UNRRA Council. Geneva, 1946. (Box 12)
  - The story of UNRRA. Washington, February 15, 1948. (Box 12)
- Pamphlets and Books, in English and French
  - The British-Yugoslav association, London (Box 13)
    - Wallace, Betty. The trial of Dr. Aloysius Stepinac, 1947. (Box 13)
    - Youth builds a railway, April 1947. (Box 13)
    - Yugoslavia faces the future: The story of the Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia, 1947. (Box 13)
    - Yugoslavia today and tomorrow, Summer 1948. (Box 13)
  - Kardelj, Edvard. The march of Yugoslavia. United Committee of Yugoslavs, London, 1945. (Box 13)
  - Marshal Tito speaks. United South Slav Committee, London, 1944. (Box 13)
  - Yugoslav youth fights back. By Captain Slavko Kumar.United South Slav Committee, London, 1944. (Box 13)
  - The epic of Yugoslavia. Described by Marshal Tito and his Generals. United South Slav Committee, London., (96pp.) (Box 13)
  - Adamic, Louis, ed. Liberation. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans. (Box 13)
  - Kardelj, Edvard. Jugoslavia's Claim to Trieste. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans. (Box 13)
  - Pirinsky, George. For a free Macedonia. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans. (Box 13)
  - Report on New Yugoslavia. By eleven members of the British Parliament. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans. (Box 13)
  - Taylor, A.J.P. Trieste. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans. (Box 13)
  - Tito, Josip Broz. The Yugoslav People's fight to live. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans., (2 copies) (Box 13)
  - Tito, Josip Broz. Yugoslavia's Foreign Policy. United Committee of South-Slavic Americans. (Box 13)
  - The Bulletin (incomplete), United Committee of South-Slavic Americans., October 1943-December 1946. (Box 13)
  - These are the people.... American Committee for Yugoslav Relief., (2 copies) (Box 13)
  - 6 untitled flyers. American Committee for Yugoslav Relief. (Box 13)
  - Extracts from field trip report of Philip E. Nelbach, United Yugoslav Relief Fund of America., 1948. (Box 13)
  - The Slavic American; a quarterly, United Yugoslav Relief Fund of America., Summer 1948 and Fall 1948. (Box 13)
  - Crimea Conference Report, Woodrow Wilson Foundation., March 1945. (Box 13)
  - How will the United Nations Work? Woodrow Wilson Foundation., July 1945. (Box 13)
  - Official documents issued during the two world wars, Woodrow Wilson Foundation., May 1945. (Box 13)
  - Pamphlets on Tito (Box 13)
    - Fast, Howard. The incredible Tito; man of the hour, 1944.; (2 copies) (Box 13)
    - Fast, Howard. Tito and his people, 1944. (Box 13)
  - Pamphlets on Yugoslavia (Box 13)
    - Cok, Ivan M. The first to resist; story of the first underground movement in this war. London, 1945. (Box 13)
    - Constitution of the Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia. Washington, D.C., 1946. (Box 13)
    - Religion in Yugoslavia.... By seven American Protestant clergymen and editors of religious journals who visited Yugoslavia in the summer of 1947. (Box 13)
    - Statuts de la jeunesse populaire Yougoslavie, 1946. (Box 13)
    - Trieste. Embassy of the Federal People's Republic of Yugoslavia, Washington D.C., 1946.; (2 copies) (Box 13)
    - Trivanovitch, Vaso. Mihailovich's treason: documentary evidence. Acorn: Ridgefield, Connecticut, 1946. (Box 13)
    - Yugoslavia: the people's revolution and education (N.E.F. Monograph no.8). London: New Education Fellowship, 1947. (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets - Various Subjects
    - Brown, Harold Chapman. What is philosophy? Published by California Labor school. (Box 13)
    - Constitution (fundamental law) of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. Moscow, 1944. (Box 13)
    - Statement of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia. Beograd, 1948. (Box 13)
    - United Nations Charter - with explanatory notes.... (International Conciliation, no.413). New York: Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1945. (Box 13)
    - Weatherwax, John M. Peace key. Los Angeles, 1946. (Box 13)
  - Books
    - Ilin, M. New Russia's primer: the story of the 5-Year Plan. Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1931. (Box 13)
    - La ligne des jeunes; oeuvre de la Jeunesse Populaire de Yougoslavie. (Box 13)
- Periodicals
  - Trideset Dana, November 1945-May 1947.; (14 items) (Box 14)
  - The Modern Quarterly. London, 1947-1948. (Box 14)
    vol.2, no.3 (Summer 1947)
    vol.3, no.1 (Winter 1947-1948)
    vol.3, no.2 (Spring 1948)
  - Changing Epoch Series (no.1-4). London. (Box 14)
    "Studies on the new economic, social, and cultural developments that are taking place in the world today."
  - The Communist: organ of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia. (Box 14)
    no.1, October 1946(2 copies, 1 bound).
    no.2, January 1947 (2 copies, 1 bound).
  - "How should we meet the threat of the New Comintern?" In Town Meeting, vol.13, no.28 (). [Bulletin of America's Town Meeting of the Air, broadcast by stations of the American Broadcasting Company]., November 4, 1947 (Box 14)
  - Viesnik Rada: le messager du travail, November 1946-May 1947. (Box 14)
  - Jež (weekly periodical, incomplete), October 13, 1945-April 24, 1948. (Box 15)
  - Kerempuh. Zagreb, 1947.; (2 issues) (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous Books and Pamphlets
  - Miscellaneous books and pamphlets in Serbo-Croatian and Russian. (Box 16)
    Includes Dnevnik, by Vladimir Dedijer, with copious notes in English.
  - Miscellaneous books and pamphlets in various languages -- not English or French. (Box 17)
- Oversize Materials
  - Group of loose-leaf art prints, apparently in Russian, 1947.; (25 leaves, accompanied by 2 leaves of text) (Box 18)
  - For a lasting peace, for a People's Democracy! Organ of the Information Bureau of the Communist Parties. Belgrade, March 1, 1948-April 1, 1949.; (9 issues) (Box 18)